Finding Aid for William G. Dow Papers, 1927-1999
Bentley Historical Library
- Professional Organizations, 1932-1977
  - Institute of Electrical & Electronic Engineers (IEEE), 1959-1977
    - Convention, New York, 1964 (Box 10)
    - Convention, New York, 1965 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 10)
    - Fellow Nominations, 1959-1963 (Box 10)
    - Southeastern Michigan Section, 1975 (Box 10)
    - Southeastern Michigan Section, 1976-1977 (Box 11)
  - Institute of Radio Engineers (IRE), 1943-1963
    - Committee on Advanced Developments, 1943-1946 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Electron Tube Research, 1954-1955; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Committee on Electron Tubes & Solid State Devices, 1957 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1939-1960 (Box 11)
    - Editorial Reports, 1941-1951 (Box 11)
    - Fellow Nominations, 1961-1963 (Box 11)
    - IRE-AIEE Merger, 1962 (Box 11)
    - Subcommittee on Small High Vacuum Tubes, 1944-1946 (Box 11)
  - NASA-DOD Space Science Committee, 1959 (Box 11)
  - National Society of Professional Engineers (NSPE), 1932-1962 (Box 11)
  - Rocket and Satellite Research Panel, 1957-1962
    - Correspondence, 1957-1962 (Box 11)
    - Minutes, November 1957-April 1960 (Box 11)
  - United States National Committee for the International Geophysical Year (USNC-IGY), Technical Panel on Rocketry, 1957-1959
    - Correspondence, 1957-1959
      - January-June 1957 (Box 11)
      - June-September 1957 (Box 11)
      - October-December 1957 (Box 11)
      - 1958 (Box 11)
      - 1959 (Box 11)
  - Upper Atmosphere Rocket Research Panel, 1954-1962
    - Correspondence, September 1954-June 1955
      - September 1954-June 1955 (Box 11)
      - October 1955-May 1956 (Box 11)
      - 1957-1962 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, October 1955-May 1956 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1957-1962 (Box 11)
- Articles, Books and Talks, 1931-1969
  The Articles, Books and Talks series contains three subseries: Published materials, Unpublished materials, and Notebooks. The Published subseries consists almost entirely of articles, arranged in chronological order by their date of publication. In some cases, folders may also contain earlier drafts and correspondence relating to the article. Full bibliographic citations for these articles can be found in the bibliography included with the Biographical materials, but neither this bibliography nor the items in this subseries provide a complete list of Dow's publications. The Unpublished subseries contains draft copies of two books: Ultra-High Frequency Space-Charge Control Tubes (1957) and Microwave Electron Beam Tubes (1958). Memoranda, talks, and articles relating to education, research, and policy can also be found in this subseries. The notebooks subseries is arranged chronologically and items are identified by title or topic. The exact purpose of these materials is unclear--some appear to be drafts of articles, others appear related to scientific research or class preparation.
  - Published, 1931-1964
    - "Reignition of Metallic A-C. Arcs in Air,", 1931 (Box 11)
    - "Probe Measurements and Potential Distribution in Copper A-C Arcs,", 1933 (Box 11)
    - "Firing Time of an Igniter Type of Tube,", 1935 (Box 11)
    - Problem Manual for Use with Fundamentals of Engineering Electronics, 1938 (Box 11)
    - "Equivalent Electrostatic Circuits for Vacuum Tubes,", 1940 (Box 11)
    - "The Generation of Ultra-High-Frequency Power at the Fifty-Kilowatt Level,", 1946 (Box 11)
    - "Transmit-Time Effects in Ultra-High-Frequency Class-C Operation,", 1947 (Box 12)
    - "Impacts of Electronics on Engineering Education,", 1949 (Box 12)
    - "Dynamic Probe Measurements in the Ionosphere,", 1949 (Box 12)
    - "Statistical Nature and Physical Concepts of Thyratron Deionization Time,", 1949 (Box 12)
    - "Supersonic Wind at Low Pressures Produced by Arc in Magnetic Field,", 1950 (Box 12)
    - "Analysis of Synchronous Conditions in the Cylindrical Magnetron Space Charge,", 1951 (Box 12)
    - "Pressures, Densities, and Temperatures in the Upper Atmosphere,", 1952 (Box 12)
    - "The Influence of a Transverse Magnetic Field on an Unconfined Glow Discharge,", 1953 (Box 12)
    - "Dynamic Probe Measurements in the Ionosphere,", 1953 (Box 12)
    - "Rocket Measurements of Upper Atmosphere Ambient Temperature and Pressure in the 30-to-75 Kilometer Region,", 1954 (Box 12)
    - "Space-Charge Behavior in Backward Space-Harmonic Beam Amplifiers and Oscillators,", 1954 (Box 12)
    - "Exploration of the Ionosphere by Means of a Langmuir-Probe Technique", 1955 (Box 12)
    - "Density-gauge Methods for Measuring Upper-air Temperature, Pressure, and Winds,", 1955 (Box 12)
    - "Physical Electronics Underlying Junction Transistor Characteristics,", 1960 (Box 12)
    - "General Aspects of Beating-Wave Amplification,", 1960 (Box 12)
    - "Experimental Study of Anomalous Electron Stream Behavior,", 1961 (Box 12)
    - "Electron Temperature Evidence for Nonthermal Equilibrium in the Ionosphere,", 1962 (Box 12)
    - "The General Perturbational Theory of Space-Harmonic Traveling-Wave Electron Interaction", 1962 (Box 12)
    - "Creating Winds of Change,", 1964 (Box 12)
  - Unpublished, 1957-1969
    - Ultra-High-Frequency Space-Charge Control Tubes, 1957
      - Chapter 1 (Box 12)
      - Chapter 2 (Box 12)
      - Chapter 3 (Box 12)
      - Figures (Box 12)
    - Microwave Electron Beam Tubes, 1958
      - Chapter 1 (Box 12)
      - Chapter 2 (two versions) (Box 12)
      - Superseded or Duplicate Figures (for both books) (Box 12)
    - "Earth Satellites and the Ultimate Pattern of Human Life,", 1959 (Box 12)
    - "Physical Electronics of Junction Transistors" and "Addendum,", 1960 (Box 12)
    - Memorandum, "Participation of the Instructional Faculty in Sponsored Research. A Critical Management-Oriented Study,", 1961 (Box 12)
    - Memorandum to L.N. Holland, "Research Policies and Practices at the University of Michigan,", 1961 (Box 12)
    - "Self-Concealment of Plasma Space-Charge Waves,", 1962 (Box 13)
    - "Continuing Education as Seen by an Engineer in Education,", 1964 (Box 13)
    - "Creation of the Winds of Change,", 1964 (Box 13)
    - "The Structuring of Engineering Decisions, Toward Creation of Human Values,", 1965 (Box 13)
    - "Space Charge Waves,", 1966 (Box 13)
    - "Estimate of the Probable Future Pattern of NASA Programs and Funding Policies,", 1967 (Box 13)
    - "Utilization of the Monopolar Diocotron Plasma Stream in Controlled Nuclear Fusion,", 1968 (Box 13)
    - "Critique of the method of using the second derivative peak in interpreting data from the Omegatron probe in thermosphere data from Puerto Rico,", 1968 (Box 13)
    - "Talk to SPRL Staff on Omegatron Data,", June 17, 1969 (Box 13)
    - "The Monopolar Ion Plasma, With Nuclear Fusion Potentialities,", undated (Box 13)
  - Notebooks, 1928-1937
    - "Where does a magnetic or dielectric field 'take hold' of a dielectric, or of a piece of magnetic material?,", October-November 1928 (Box 13)
    - "Re-Ignition of Metallic A.C. Arcs in Air," June-, July-August 1930 (Box 13)
    - Traveling Waves [?], 1930-1931 (Box 13)
    - "Sheath Transients (Computations),", 1934 (Box 13)
    - Time-Study material, 1932-1935 (Box 13)
    - "Analysis of the Electric Field of a Triode having a Grid-like Cathode,", Fall 1936 (Box 13)
    - "Electron Ballistics; Space-Charge Flow in Simple Geometries,", 1937 (Box 13)
- Topical Files, 1929-1970
  The Topical Files series contains a group of files on Conferences and Meetings (arranged alphabetically); many of these events are related to Dow's Professional Organizations. There is also a small group of materials related to the Space Physics Research Lab (SPRL). Dow kept files on his many business and research trips. These are arranged together, and contain correspondence and other material relating to Dow's investigations of industrial and military electronics research laboratories.
  - Conferences and Meetings, 1934-1967
    - American Geophysical Union (AGU), 1967 (Box 13)
    - "Air Force Basic Research in Universities and Industry,", 1960 (Box 13)
    - Boulder, 1965 (Box 13)
    - Cornell Electronics Conference, 1934 (Box 13)
    - "Engineering Aspects of Magnetohyrdodynamics" Symposia, 1964-1966 (Box 13)
    - "Expanding Horizons of Engineering Education,", 1964 (Box 13)
    - "First National Conference on Automotive, Electrical and Electronics Engineering,", 1964 (Box 13)
    - MIT Conference on Physical Electronics, 1947 (Box 13)
    - Rocket and Satellite Research Panel, 1959 (Box 13)
    - Rocket and Satellite Research Panel, 1967 (Box 13)
    - Seminar at Urbana, 1966 (Box 13)
  - Degree in Space Science, 1964-1966 (Box 13)
  - Electron Optics, 1957-1962 (Box 13)
  - Engineering Curriculum Study, 1929-1930; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Gifts to University of Michigan (Box 13)
  - IST Organization, 1970 (Box 13)
  - Langmuir Probes (at SPRL), 1966 (Box 13)
  - Monopolar Plasma for Nuclear Fusion, 1959-1966 (Box 13)
  - Not-for-profit Research Institute, 1966 (Box 13)
  - National Science Foundation (NSF) Review, 1963 (Box 13)
  - Patents, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Puerto Rico Launches, 1968 (Box 14)
  - Radio Research Lab (Harvard), 1947-1952 (Box 14)
  - San Marco Satellite Omegatron Experiment, 1967-1968 (Box 14)
  - Space Physics Research Lab (SPRL), 1966-1970
    - Building, 1969-1970 (Box 14)
    - "Effort Records,", 1966-1969 (Box 14)
    - General, 1966 (Box 14)
    - Library, 1966 (Box 14)
  - Trips, 1941-1970
    - Western Trip, 1941 (Box 14)
    - Eng, 1942-1945 (Box 14)
    - European Trip, 1953 (Box 14)
    - Report on Visits to European Electron Tube Laboratories, 1953 (Box 14)
    - Western Trip, 1955 (Box 14)
    - Eastern Trip, 1956 (Box 14)
    - Houston (Manned Space Flight Center), 1966-1970 (Box 14)
    - Boston (Microsystems), 1967 (Box 14)
    - Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL), 1967 (Box 14)
    - Wallops Is, 1968 (Box 14)
    - World Tour, 1969-1970 (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan Electrical Engineering Department, 1965 (Box 14)
  - War Surplus Equipment, 1945-1947; 2 folders (Box 14)
- Correspondence, 1947-1981
  The Correspondence series is organized alphabetically by the correspondent's last name.
  - Arguelles, Camilo R. (Box 14)
  - Arnikar, H.J. (Box 14)
  - Beaman, Duncan, 1977-1981 (Box 14)
  - Beck, A.H.W. (Box 14)
  - Board, T.F.A. (Box 14)
  - Bogle, A.G. (Box 14)
  - Carignan, George, 1966-1970 (Box 14)
  - Castellanos, Dario, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Chatterjee, Rajeswari, 1949-1963; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Chevigny, George (Box 15)
  - Cogneaux, Marcus (Box 15)
  - Condell, William, 1962 (Box 15)
  - Correa, Charles and Monica (Box 15)
  - Correa, W.R. (Box 15)
  - De Koranyi, Laszlo and Gilda (Box 15)
  - Egloff, Robert (Box 15)
  - Errabi, Mohammed (Box 15)
  - Ettlinger, A.E. (Box 15)
  - Gabor, D., Dr. Ing. (?) (Box 15)
  - Fujisawa, Toshio (Box 15)
  - Hayasaka, Takeshi (Box 15)
  - Hok, Gunnar and Ruth (Box 15)
  - Hok, Ruth (Box 15)
  - Hu, Han Peking (Box 15)
  - Hughes, Hong Kong (Box 15)
  - Kenmoku, M. (Box 15)
  - Kleynen (Box 15)
  - Kobayashi, Koji (Box 15)
  - Malleson, (Mullard) (Box 15)
  - Melunke (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940-1977; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Morgan, Joe and Pitaya (Box 15)
  - Morita, Kiyosho (Box 15)
  - Nakamura, Kiroshi (Dr. Eng.) (Box 15)
  - Nazareth Family (Bombay India) (Box 15)
  - Nemoto, Tadao (Box 15)
  - Nishimura, Margarita (Box 15)
  - O'Brien, Brian (Box 15)
  - Ozawa, Masayoshi, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Pennington, A.J., 1978 (Box 15)
  - Rea, Donald G., 1970 (Box 15)
  - Reich, Herbert J. (Box 15)
  - Reyes, H.R. (Philippines) (Box 15)
  - Ristenbatt, M. P. (Box 15)
  - Ristrow, Hugo (Box 15)
  - Rittershofer, L.F., Patmos, William (Box 15)
  - Reclus, Roca (Box 15)
  - Romanowitz, H.A., 1947-1954 (Box 15)
  - Romney, George (Box 15)
  - Ross, Howard and Jeanette (Box 15)
  - Rozian, I. W. (Box 15)
  - Rowe, Joseph E. (Box 15)
  - Rutishauser, Dorothy (Ayres) (Box 15)
  - Salisbury, Winfield W. (Box 15)
  - Satterthwaite, P.C., 1966-1967 (Box 15)
  - Satyam, M. (Box 15)
  - Schmalz (Box 15)
  - Scruggs, Jim and Jane, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Segovia, Jose (Box 15)
  - Shepherd, W.G. (Box 15)
  - Shlanta, Gay (Box 15)
  - Siegel, K.M. and Ruth (Box 15)
  - Simons, Helen (Box 16)
  - Singh, Amarjit (Box 16)
  - Smith, Newburn (Box 16)
  - Sparrow, Fred and Nan (Box 16)
  - Spears, Geo. and Juliette (Ayres) (Box 16)
  - Spencer, Nelson and Ginny (Box 16)
  - Spooner, Willett and Vera (Box 16)
  - Staebler, Neil (Box 16)
  - Stainsby, Mr. (Box 16)
  - Steiner, H.C. (Box 16)
  - Stanger, F.J.W. (Box 16)
  - Stirton, Bill and Kathy (Box 16)
  - Stockard, Jewell (Box 16)
  - Stout, M.B. (Box 16)
  - Strand, John (Box 16)
  - Strickland, Harold (Box 16)
  - Sueta, Prof. and Mrs. (Box 16)
  - Swinyard, W.O. (Box 16)
  - Taddeucci, Chiarina (Box 16)
  - Tai, Chen-To (Box 16)
  - Tallmadge, H.A. (Box 16)
  - Talpey, T.E. and Betty (Box 16)
  - Tanner, W.P. (Box 16)
  - Teberg, E. J. (Box 16)
  - Terman, Fred and Sybil (Box 16)
  - Thurston, A.E. (Box 16)
  - Tieman, Chas Marc (Box 16)
  - Tiffany, Lyle (Box 16)
  - Timoshenko, Gregory (Box 16)
  - Titiev, Mischa and Estelle (Box 16)
  - Uchimaru, Kiyoshi, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Vadhana, S.T. (Box 16)
  - Vance, Evelyn (Box 16)
  - Vivian, W.E. (Box 16)
  - Volcker, Paul A. (Box 16)
  - Volkholz, Klaus L. (Box 16)
  - Vowels, Prof. Rex (Box 16)
  - Warnecke, Dr. (Box 16)
  - Warren, S. Reid, Jr. (Box 16)
  - Waterman, M.H. (Box 16)
  - Weber, Ernest, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Wedel, Ted (Box 16)
  - Welch, H.W. (Box 16)
  - Wernette, Phil and Eleanor (Box 16)
  - Wheeler, H.A. (Box 16)
  - Whipple, Fred L., 2 folders (Box 16)
  - White, A.E. and Elsie (Box 16)
  - White, Carl and Eileen (Box 16)
  - White, John (Box 16)
  - Wilcox, Ruth and Ralph (Box 16)
  - Wilder, Ray L. (Box 16)
  - Williamson, Gwen (Box 16)
  - Willow Run Labs, 1970 (Box 16)
  - Winter, Stanislaus (Box 16)
  - Wisnefski, Gladys (Box 16)
  - Wisusik, Mildred (Box 16)
  - Woodson, H.H. (Box 16)
  - Young, Andrew (Box 16)
  - Yu, T.S. (Box 16)
  - Zahl, Harold (Box 16)
  - Zarabi, M. J. (Box 16)
  - Zissis, George (Box 16)
- Photographs, 1940-1964
  Photographs includes images of Dow teaching, in his office, and as a member of various professional groups. Other photographs are scattered throughout the collection in different subject files
  - Arecibo Ionospheric Observatory, Puerto Rico, June 1964 (Box 16)
  - Groups (Box 16)
  - Personal (lecturing, in office, in lab, 104th birthday celebration) (Box 16)